[Music]
do
foreign
[Music]
do
come on
ready for you 2020 water
[Music]
299.
happy birthday
[Music]
but she was there to keep my spirits up
for that thankfully
[Music]
come on
to start may we invite everyone to
answer our call questions
flashed on your screens right now
[Music]
one who answered for those who haven't
answered answered yet or sent their
votes please don't close the form and
submit your answers now
thank you
[Music]
um
foreign
[Music]
well hello everyone welcome it's good to
see all of you over here my name is
james deakin
and let me all welcome you to the
afternoon's financial wellness webinar
now
today's session is part of the wellness
webinar series that's brought to you by
the leading global life insurance
company
manulife today we'll be talking about
how you can prepare for a better
financial future
by putting your money to work or simply
investing
investing is an important step to
achieving your best possible financial
future because
it offers additional income and
opportunities to grow your wealth
and there are different types of
investments here as well one
is investment linked insurance that
takes us a step further as it combines
two opportunities in one the possibility
of higher returns
in the future while still providing life
security and protection for you
and your loved ones now i'm sure you'll
want to hear
more and more about this which is why
we've invited two subject matter experts
our first guest will be talking about
market outlook for 2021
while our second guest will help us
understand
what investment life insurance is all
about
throughout this program if you have any
comments or questions for our speakers
just go ahead and send them by the q a
box
at the bottom right side of your screens
and later on
our guests will also be participating in
the q and a session this is going to be
great because
aside from learning a lot manulife
philippines will also be giving away
5 000 pesos worth of sodexo gcs
so stay tuned for that okay it's time to
get
to meet our first speaker he is the head
of wealth of sales of manulife asset
management trust company
he has more than 20 years of experience
in retail banking and wealth management
he's also a chartered wealth manager a
registered financial planner
an sec certified fixed income salesman
and an sec certified
investment solicitor to give us an
update on the latest market outlook for
2021 let us all welcome mr
cedric matubis
[Music]
good afternoon said hi welcome how are
you
great james uh happy to be here that's
awesome stuff so are we we got so many
people tuned in said they got
over a thousand people right now and you
know what they're a very engaged bunch
so i'll get straight to it we're close
to ending the first quarter of 2021.
how is the market doing today and what
opportunities are we seeing
uh james here to date as of march 5
yields are slightly higher
by an average of around 80 basis points
uh while the psei
is slightly down around three percent
having said that we believe that the
outlook for 2021
is fairly positive and we do see this
temporary
dip in the market as a good opportunity
for long-term investors particularly
those
looking at philippine stocks well that's
great how are we advising clients with
the new investable assets in today's
market situation
as always we advise clients to do two
things uh
one is to invest long term and two to
diversify
the prospects for 2021 uh indeed look
positive as i will discuss later
but there are still risks out there
people who have
a long-term investment horizon and who
have diversified portfolios
will usually have a better investing
experience
no matter what happens well that's
precisely why we're here today thank you
sid i'm sure everyone is excited
as i am to hear about all your updates
on the market outlook for 2021
so let's get to it shall we great
um good afternoon everyone so um
uh i'd like to start off with a
quick look at various
macro economic updates and i'd like to
start off with interest rates
so on the next slide you can see here
the yield curve and we can see that
interest rates have really dropped from
a year ago
the white curve representing the rates
from last year and the green one just
last february but one can also note that
the more recent trend is upwards with
december 2020 being the blue one and
september 2020 the pink one
so we do believe that while years are
still low compared to last year
mainly due to the cuts to the policy
rate of the bsp in 2020
there is indeed pressure for yields to
go up given potential higher issuance of
government debt
this year and also higher u.s threshold
yields
in recent weeks on the next slide we
talk about inflation um
last january you can see here that there
was an uptick uh
to the tune of 4.2 percent forcing the
bsp to revise their full year for
forecast to 4 from 3.2
originally the bsp however expressed
their belief that this was transitory
and was merely due to supply-side
disruptions relating to the recent
typhoons and the african swine fever
infestation
not shown in the chart is the february
inflation number because it was
recently just recently announced a few
days ago which is around 4.7 percent
which is still within the what bsp
expected uh for the month
inflation continues to be something that
we are looking at considering price
stability can
impact the ability of the bsp to
keep rates low um on a good note on the
next slide
you can see here the gdp forecasts for
2021 and they are indeed encouraging
5.9 from the world bank 6.5 percent from
the adb and 6.5
from the imf uh this coming from four
straight quarters of contraction in 2020
um these institutions cite the following
as drivers to the recovery number one
renewed infraspending number two gradual
recovery of the private sector
and number three the support of the
central bank in terms of uh giving
of having an accommodative monetary
policy
on the next slide we we see here
something of a risk
and we're watching out for uh this is
the level of government borrowing for
this year
so for 2020 it's very obvious that we
had uh
actual borrowing was higher than both
the 2020 plan
and the actual borrowing the previous
year obviously as the government
fiscal spending increased to support the
country during
covet 19. for 2021 we believe potential
higher issuance of government bonds
may bring headwinds to the bond market
on the stock market
on the next slide we can see here how
volatile it was and you
you just have to look at the chart and
you can immediately grasp the volatility
and if you can see also there the
volatility also had
was always in line with what is
happening with kovid so for
the first quarter uh because of the
start of local transmission you can see
here the big drop
in second quarter because of the lifting
of ezq in
ncr you also see the big jump
and in the fourth quarter as optimism
over successful phase three vaccine
trials
you know uh influence the market to uh
to come
to come back not in uh encourage
investors to come back
and you can see the big appreciation in
prices there
to further show how volatile it was like
on the next slide you can see a table
here uh of how wild it was the greens
and reds
alternating against each other for every
quarter and
just to drive how volatile it was uh uh
and uh
attended at one point uh during the year
an investor could have lost 47
almost half his money while at other
points another could have gained 78
so that was uh that was how how volatile
it was
for the fourth quarter um in the next
slide you can see that the
one of the drivers for the gain in the
in the
stock market was the um
the drop in daily new covet cases and
and the and positivity rates from the
highs of
august and september so we were
experiencing around a thousand just a
thousand or close to two thousand cases
daily new cases uh
late in the year so that encouraged uh
you know investors to come back
and on the next slide you can also see
here
that um the reduced number of infection
cases also
encourage mobility to improve now so we
can see here
although we have not gone back to normal
you can see here for example
from the low of negative 73 percent for
workplace activity versus the
pre-covered baseline we are now just
around
negative 10 and you can see the drops in
almost all other categories like
going to the malls using public
transport et cetera et cetera
in the last four days however daily
cases have increased to around 3 000
and this is something that we are
closely watching obviously uh
and this will definitely have an impact
on markets
on the next slide um you can see here
what the government
has been doing in terms of reforms and
increased spending
to support employment growth and the the
in fact the impact that we'll have
on our forecasts on um
unemployment and also infrastructure
spending and you can see here that the
trends are going to
at least approximate pre-covered numbers
uh in 2021 and in 2022 on the next slide
specifically you can see here what the
government
has done um to make that happen and that
would be uh
the national budget for example has a 10
percent increase compared to 2020.
compared to the 2020 budget you have the
second
bayanihan to spending low extension
that will carry over 147 billion of
unused funds to
this year you have the crate bill that
will help
corporations uh you know it will also
cut corporate taxes it will help attract
foreign
uh investments and generate employment
and finally the fist bill
that will provide fiscal incentives to
banks who will sell their non-par
non-performing loans and for close
assets to
special purpose vehicles in terms of
corporate earnings uh we see here that
the positive um you know the outlook on
the plastic business
environment and because of excitement
over
uh possible vaccine rollouts we can see
here that
forecasts for corporate earnings uh
growth are double-digit across
all the members of the main index uh
with the main index itself
expected to have an average aps growth
of 54 percent
uh and with with with sectors like the
financial sector and the consumer
discretionary sector in the industrial
sector as well
leading the pack so um
to summarize uh 2021
is uh poised to be a recovery uh but
there are still risks so on the next
slides we'll show you these things
um interest rates are expected to be you
know somewhat low
uh and inflationable manageable
inflation manageable at least for the
first half of the year
the expectations of a vaccine roll out
provide some optimism for mobility to
trend higher and for economic
activity to you know show sign of signs
of going back to normal
which can result then to higher gdp
growth and corporate earnings
but as mentioned earlier there are still
risks out there despite of this
positive outlook like higher than
expected government borrowing
risks pertaining to ovid like increased
cases etc etc
so that's why we still encourage people
to look at this
market with the positive but have a
long-term
investment horizon that is my last slide
james and i am looking forward to answer
questions later
well thank you very much for that said
for all of those updates uh
certainly a lot to absorb a lot to learn
indeed these insights
will help us become more knowledgeable
and confident about investing i could
see all those erratic
figures you were showing wow so much as
they say to
unpack here now if you have any
questions for zed please just type them
in in the q a
box at the bottom of your screen and uh
he will answer them later on
during our q a session before we move on
to our second speaker
let's check out the audience's pulse and
our poll questions are here
and to update us on those results well
we have one of manulife's associate
area heads vanessa de las reyes joining
us today hi there vanessa
hello james and good afternoon to
everyone i'm here today to give the
results of our quick
online fall survey now it's nice to see
that our audience today is very
interested in the topic
our first question was why are you
investing
why are you saving up or investing and
the choices are retirement
child's education wealth diversification
and growth
health emergencies and 46 percent
has answered that they are saving up for
retirement
now manulife has insurance plans that
can actually act as a retirement fund
these plans guarantee lifetime insurance
protection for you
and your family while securing your hard
earned money
now let's look at the second question
why are you currently where are you
currently invested
and the choices are stocks real estate
insurance uitf or mutual funds bank time
deposits
or not so far now i see a lot of our
viewers today are currently invested in
insurance with 56
now lastly our third question is do you
know
how investment linked life insurance
works
yes or no and 75
said that they know they know how
investment like life insurance works
now before i turn this over to james we
will flash another ball question
and the question is what is your
investment appetite this 2021
and the choices are confident or not too
confident
i need advice from any from an expert
now i hope
everyone answered because later we will
reveal the results and we will also pick
one lucky audience member
who will win 5 000 worth of sodexo gcs
now once again i encourage everyone to
join our conversation by typing in your
thoughts in the q a box
later our guests will address all of
these in the q
a session now back to you james
thank you vanessa and i like i said
earlier we have a very engaged bunch
not only are are they engaged but it
turns out they're very well informed too
very impressive uh with the amount of
people that not only reacted
all but the answers as well so people
are really grasping it you know what i'm
very impressed because i thought a lot
of people thought
the best investment was or what they
were saving up for was like the shoppie
sales or the lazada sales but no
it's good that they're saving for their
future i like that
and also uh the poll results very very
interesting
um there moving on we'd like to talk
about
uh some investment linked life insurance
policies now
or variable universal life plans
and for that i'd like to introduce to
you our next speaker who will share with
us
how this type of plan can help you enjoy
potential higher investment returns
liquidity and light protection he is one
of the country's
most knowledgeable and experienced
financial experts
he's a stock market trader entrepreneur
international keynote speaker he is also
the ceo
of stock smart inc and a national
bookstore
best-selling author of five stock market
and investing books
ladies and gentlemen join me in
welcoming mr
marvin guillermo
thank you so much thank you so much
james for that very very warm
introduction and while i was listening
to what said was talking about a while
ago
it was so amazing because my style when
it comes to investing is to really look
at where
the economy is headed because as you
start to
drill down and know where the economy is
it will also allow you to
analyze on how you're supposed to go
about your investments and
before i all i begin i'd also like to
honor manulife for creating this event
it's such an honor to
see companies create events like this
because i really believe that financial
education financial information is
something that should be front and
center right now it's
it's okay to entertain yourself it's
okay to be updated with
news that's going around in the country
but people need to realize it
your future is not about waiting for the
economy to get
better sometimes your future is about
you
being faithful with what you have right
now and be better
and invest so that you can determine
your future don't wait for it to just
fall on your lap but you take control of
it and that being said
uh people know me as a stock market guy
and what's so interesting about
uh what zed talked about earlier is it's
really true we are in the midst of a
recession
and that's what i always say recessions
are cyclical it's not
a question whether a recession will
happen but it's a question of
when and a greater and bigger question
is what you are doing in the midst of it
because i really believe that in the
midst of uncertainty
there's so much opportunity out there
and what's not talked about is they say
people always say that recall that
recessions are cyclical but here's the
thing
recoveries are two it's not a question
whether a recovery will happen
it's only a question of when and a
greater question from one investor to
another
is what we are doing right now in the
midst of us trying to recover
because sayami the opportunity is when
everything is not so
fruity yet when everything is not so
good yet because when everything is so
good already
sometimes valuations will be higher
sometimes you don't get
to invest at a price that you want to
invest in
especially if you are investing for the
long term and
unbeknownst to many uh if you if you
could show the next slide please
people always look at me as a guy that's
all in in the stock market but
i'm a person who loves investing
by distributing items and creating
multiple streams of income
because i know most of you here are so
in tune with investing
but yeah we have to realize that the
name of the game is about
distributing assets that will work hard
for you
and if you are employed it's also
amazing that you get to focus on your
job
it's so amazing that while you're
focusing on your craft
while you're focusing on what you want
to do you have other assets that are
working hard on the sidelines
and in the next slide i want to share
different uh
pieces know of how i distribute my
investments and how i would
somehow classify it and a quick
narrative on how i would distribute it
is by three number one
growth cash flow and investments that
would allow me to hedge what do i mean
about that
my intention for investments that would
allow me to grow is basically this
as you all know and i'm sure looking at
the surveying a lot of you are already
investing in different types of asset
classes
you would know that investments that
would allow you and would give you
growth
are items that somehow would give you
volatility
somehow that at some point it will not
it will not be investments that would go
up in
a day or two or three or four but those
growth investments are there to give you
long-term capital appreciation
and my technique for that is to find
investments that if i plant and
invest them in them right now
5 10 15 years along the line it will
definitely beat
bonds it will definitely be time
deposits and it will be a stable asset
class
in la in conjunction to my business or
in conjunction to those of you who are
also working
second is cash flow my cash flow
investments for me are
investments that will give me
predictability of income cash flow
investments for me are investments that
it may not grow as fast as those
growth investments but it will give me
predictability it will give me income
on a monthly quarterly or at least a
bi-annual basis
and the the way you would segment it is
they say
when you are younger and and please do
note that the way you structure your
investments
and your technique should be the younger
you are
the more you should be focused on items
that will give you growth and
just just to assume no i think majority
of the people that are here are
in their 30s in their 40s some are in
your 20s meaning you have a longer time
horizon the longer time horizon the more
you get to have the ability to double
down
and to invest but you have to realize
also that there will come a point in
time that you will be
that you will get older as you get older
you need to also position on investments
that will give you predictability
especially and all of us figured that
out last year that
as markets dropped some of those growth
investments
as what said showed us there were
volatility in it
but investments that gave you cash flow
no matter
how bad the market was would have given
you also cash in return
and lastly the third one and this is not
what a lot of people would like to talk
about
it's very very important that you need
to have as part of your portfolio
a segment that would allow you to hedge
hedge in a way that it may not
perform as good as your growth
investments it may not be sexy
but it's there for the very purpose that
if things don't go the way you want it
to go if the
economy turns bad or if suddenly
something happens to you
that your ability to earn more won't be
there you have that stable
asset class that could protect you as
well and that's what i want to submit to
all of you you need
all three you need something that will
grow you need something that will give
you predictable income and you need
something that will give you cash flow
and what's so interesting about that in
the next slide and this is what
not a lot of people know was this when i
started investing i've been investing
for
over 14 years now and as i started
investing in my early 20s
people thought i directly went into the
stock market
but one of my first investments was i
got into a variable unit link insurance
i got into a ba i got i got into a
balanced fund
because with with the very notion that
this was something that i i never grew
up with
and i i know for most of us as filipinos
it's not part of our culture
to talk about investing and at that time
i was employed and at that time i was
creating businesses that's
i need to have exposure to investments
but in the same way
while i'm not an expert yet while i
don't know as much
i need something already that will allow
me to get my feet wet
and what's interesting about that in the
next slide as i started to
do a deep dive on on what vu els
are i i realized that hmm
vu els as you can see the next slide are
composed of two particular things
stocks and bonds and as i started to as
i started to add
as i started to analyze it majority of
people would
would see that if you invest in stocks
it's a bit volatile it's a bit scary
it's a bit risky it's something that
may you may lose your money in it but
as i started to dig deeper and i hope
that this adds value to you right now
while we're in the midst of a lot of
uncertainty and still volatility that
you have to look at it from the lens
that every time you invest in a fund in
an equity fund in a balanced fund that
has exposure to the stock market what it
gives you
is a piece of ownership in the largest
companies in the philippines
it could be ayala it could be sm it
could be the largest supermarket it
could be the largest telecom company
and the thing about that is this when
people say it's risky
i i i want to i want to segment this to
all of you that
if you start your own business or
partner because a friend
oh start is really nothing milky or
let's start this
shawarma or let's go into this franchise
i want to submit the idea that
that might be even riskier than you
investing in companies that are built to
last
and please remember this i like what
said i like what cedric said about
uh about the chart that the philippine
stock exchange
dropped not because the companies inside
the equity funds were bad
but because there was a pandemic that
nobody predicted
no one at the end of 2019 knew that by
march or april uh 2020
90 of the philippine economy would be
shut down so please do note this
prices dropped not because the company
were it was mismanaged that they were
doing bad
it was it was it just dropped because
there was a lot of uncertainty
and if there's one thing we all know
about investing
is uncertainty would cause people to
stay in the sidelines
but what i want to submit to all of you
is i saw it from your results
most of you are in it for retirement day
and if you're in it for retirement and
you are
20 30 40 years old and you have a very
very long timeline
times like this should be a position for
you should be
should be a time for you that you get to
position and buy things lower
especially if what you're investing on
melaman especially if you what you're
investing on us what i've mentioned
will be part of the recovery because
here's the thing
i've i've i've seen three crashes in
our economy uh 1997 crash i wasn't
investing yet i was young but i was able
to experience two
the 2008 crash and what we saw last year
and it's not a matter of just being
optimistic about it
it's a matter of history statistics and
math that every time a crash
happens it's followed by a very very
strong
recovery it's followed by unprecedented
growth
as well why because as you can see also
right now companies that got hit
are starting to pivot companies that got
hit are starting to
get bet are starting to get better and
adapt to this new normal
so what i'm saying is this for those of
you
who want exposure to equity funds
and at that time when i when i started
out i i saw it firsthand how markets
dropped during the 2008 recession
and i i knew it that after this is
after this is all said and done these
companies that are built to last will
continue to go higher
and if you look at it also i i started
to invest using balanced funds and
what's interesting about balanced funds
is this um it's a counterbalance
to stocks meaning it you have
bonds that give you the component that
if there's so much volatility in the
stock market
the bond market can give you this type
of protection
in a way that if things aren't so well
the bond market can give you stability
and i like that because looking at it
positions in bond markets would give you
with would buy government bonds which
are guaranteed
and for those of you who are risk-averse
it's still a good position
to be in so that's one of the things
that i liked about it and
up until now no from 2007 to where we
are right now my position still stands
that it's a very very good way for you
to be not just exposed in the market
but have companies that
think about it this way when you invest
in equity funds you get positioned in
the largest banks the largest power
players which
in apero we cannot buy our own meralco
we cannot buy our own telco
but because of funds you get to have a
piece of the philippine economy
and it's time for filipinos
it's time for us also to make money off
of it
looking at the next slide is one of the
reasons why i think it's so amazing is
diversity meaning i mentioned about the
largest companies in the philippines but
not just that day
but because it's so spread across just
looking about just looking at the index
alone
like what cedric said a while ago 30
stocks
distributed from telcos banks
supermarkets conglomerates which
don't go down at the same time which are
totally unrelated to each other which
gives you exposure to the philippine
economy
what i'm saying is this if you believe 5
10 15 years from now that after this
pandemic is over that the economy will
be
massively better than where we are right
now investing in vols investing in
equity funds
gives you issue banking on the
philippine economy is you banking on
that
when we're all back to normal then we
all get to go
out again the philippines is a
consumption driven economy
where majority of people in the
philippines
like to spend like what james said uh
shoppi lasada as filipinos spend the
economy
will drive and our our demographic just
keeps growing and growing and growing
and growing and growing
in the next slide i one of the reasons
why i was so attracted to it especially
when i was starting out and
if you are new to the world of investing
i hope that you grasp this
when you invest in the stock market you
have to decide what stock do i need to
buy
how many stocks do i need to buy if i
want to put in 1 million pesos or 500
000 pesos how do i transit do i trash
do i buy 20 first do i put 50
and then later on six months along the
line i have money what stock do i buy or
do i hold or do i sell
the value of equity funds is that you
have fund managers to do it for you
you i i saw that as an advantage on
on my end because they at that point
i knew that they had experience more
than what i had
so if you want exposure and you don't
want the nitty-gritty
how many shares of ayala should i buy is
it
energy or should i buy should i buy a
telco company should i buy a water
company what should i buy how should i
proportion it if you don't want that
headache
and you just want exposure then i really
believe fund managers
are there to do the selection for you
and they're there also for so
so you can uh pick and select and time
properly without the hassle because
please remember this
in the world of investing uh investments
are supposed to
work hard for you meaning if you're
glued to your screen
every second of the day trying to watch
your investment
then it's not an investment anymore it's
you
being an employee to your own investment
and for those who want
passive income i really believe that
equity funds
via vuls will do a very very good job
and number four
um next slide please um
i was i was dabbling a bit about it
already
but when i was starting out it allowed
me to leverage time
it allowed me to leverage that oh
no i get to have exposure to the stock
market
and the bond market but in the same time
i get to start other businesses and i
still get to be good at what i do
so here's the thing as much as i like
everyone
to be stock traders stock investors have
exposure to the stock market
or start their own business i really
believe not everyone will be
entrepreneurs
but a lot of us can have exposure to the
largest businesses in the country
and now you're not just leveraging the
largest businesses but because you're
investing in a fund you're leveraging
the expertise
and the skills of those fund managers as
well so
um next slide please my technique in all
of this know as i started to invest
and i hope that this gives you
conviction in all of this is
next the next slide will show that my
goal
when i invested was my retirement and
which is
front and center to what all of you guys
were clicking a while ago in the survey
when i started out i was already
planning for my retirement when i was in
my early 20s because
and and you guys who answered retirement
are doing it right there because it's
not a question whether you will stop
working it's only a question of when and
the sooner you prepare for it the better
and what's interesting about that is you
invest not because you want to make
money you invest because you want to hit
a goal
and my goal was retirement my goal was
when i hit this
age and at that point i was thinking 60
western retirements
but think about it for those of you who
are in your 30s or in your 40s or at
least those of you also who
are in your 20s if you start investing
right now or if you double down right
now for retirement say at 60
you have 20 at least 20 to 40 good years
of time that you get to invest you have
20 to 40 years also that
i was thinking that funny and stoxy like
what cedric said a while ago may
volatility
there will be times now but my mentality
was
i'm investing in my 20s say if a crash
happens 15 years from now
which it which which is also likely that
there will be another crash later on
i would have been in my 30s at that time
and
knowing that indica
extra it would have been a buying
opportunity for me
and please remember it could be
retirement for me
for some of you who placed other goals
that's well and good
always in please remember this whatever
you earn
from your investments they are always a
byproduct of how you structure your
goals never ever ever chase returns
first returns will always be a byproduct
of how you plan
because that's the most important thing
you invest to meet a need you invest to
meet
a goal so that when markets drop you
don't get rattled
because your your motivator for you
investing
is your plan is your goal and i'll tell
you this
i mentioned a while ago that recessions
will happen
there will be another recession eight
years from now 10 years from now 12
years from now 14 years from now i don't
know when
it's not a question i don't know what
will be the cause of it
but it will happen and the sooner you
prepare
and have a strategy also when that
happens
it will allow you to structure your
investments well
next in the next slide um
aside from plotting a goal when you
invest
my technique for conviction is always
for the long term and this may sound
cliche
but it's really there will be times that
as you invest
six months one year it's not performing
1.5 years two years it's not performing
it's even lower but if you are looking
at it from a
long-term perspective that's a reason
for you to buy the dip that's a reason
for you to double down that's a reason
for you
to put in and i'm sharing this not from
something i read
of a book i'm telling you that it works
there are certain investments that i
started 2007 that
on 2009 2010 they were not working
but 2012 2013 and once things started to
improve you saw you would see the
benefits of it please remember this
it's the boring things in life that will
make you rich
it's not the sexy things what you see
around you people always what get rich
quick get rich quick it's not like that
day
sometimes it's when no one wants to
invest no one wants it
everyone's scared that's the position
for you to start
allocating that's the time for you to be
able to
come in and people would ask me in 2008
can i invest in 2008 here's the thing
i didn't know the market would go up in
2009. i didn't know it would rally to
highs in 2010 2011.
i just knew that in the midst of
uncertainty recoveries will happen
and ladies and gentlemen we are sitting
in another
area we're not at the lowest anymore but
we are still at the point where there's
still uncertainty we're still not yet
out of the woods
and i want you to picture this example
when you're looking at the long term
think about bgc
bgc year 2000 so bran
because no one knew what it would be
fast forward 2021 bgc is all
primed up like singapore like a first
world country first world city
but here's the thing the prices are
higher you have a choice
you can you can think long term but you
can invest while
everything is not yet as nice because
when everything is not yet as nice
it's cheaper or you can wait
before when things get better when the
pandemic is gone
but here's what i know prices won't be
as slow as what it is right now
anyways next slide please
and you could use this opportunity
and every time i would see dips
especially for
for my funds especially for equity funds
for balanced funds
it would be an opportunity for me to
accumulate
please remember what's what's more
important than them gains that you will
get
is the base that you put the how you
accumulate your funds
people always want a new investment you
might be getting 100 return don't focus
on that
focus why let me submit this idea to you
if you have an investment that earns a
hundred percent per ten thousand
language
earning a hundred percent on that will
just give you another ten thousand pesos
but what if from 20 or 30 or 40 years
old you start accumulating
from your salary from your bonuses you
become very very intentional then you
put in money
what's interesting about that is this at
certain points
even if your investment would dip
but because you started accumulating
with a larger base
by the time you retire that money that
you started putting in your 20s and
your 30s would have been massive already
now
next slide please
uh what gives what would give you
conviction also
is this please remember that every time
you invest
you only invest your excess and i just
want to balance it out because sometimes
after webinars like this
never put in money that you would need
for today only put in money that
is an excess of what you need
to meet in three months from now it
should be something that you should put
in and just forget about it
because if it's something that you can
forget the volatilities that happen
in 2021 won't matter the volatility the
the drops that you would see
won't scare you and my gauge every time
i would invest let me give an example
for example you want to invest
someone see james feeding or somebody
else investing in 10 million pesos
all right so if you would think about 10
million pesos
always think about what if this drops by
can i sleep soundly at night if the
answer is no
then you lower it five million pesos is
this something that i can
sleep soundly at night if the answer is
no then you lower it again
you invest for the long term but only
invest something that
if it goes to zero okay you're you want
to fight
in the mother-in-law it has to be an
amount that you can live with in spite
of the volatility
so in the next slide this is what
insurance is so
what's what makes insurance so
interesting uh
having a vul allowed me to have a hedge
but on the next slide this is what makes
it interesting
it gives me both a hedge of protection
and also investments and on the next
slide
i've been i've been investing for over
14 years now and fast forward to where
we are today i would say that
my exposure in equity funds was one of
the best things that i've ever done
because it allowed me it allowed me to
not just
see how it works but it it builds your
acumen
it allows you to have experience meaning
the more you start investing the more
you get entrenched
by it you will realize that drops are
normal
that the next time this happens next
time a drop will happen seven years from
now
when you see that oh after 2008 we
recovered back again
that will give you the confidence that
eight or ten years from now
when you look back as markets drop again
i saw this happen in 2020 i already know
what to do
and that's what i want to encourage you
on you double down and you spend a lot
of time
building your your base right now um
i'll just run through this slides but
these are these are a couple of things
that i want to impart on you on the
on the value also of vol life insurance
is not about predicting the future
because it's about being responsible
because we can never
know what will happen later on but we
we ca what we can do is to be faithful
with what we have right now
so life insurance for me is about
protecting my cash flow next slide
please
but also protection from being a burden
meaning if things don't
go the way i want it my life insurance
can protect me my vul can protect me
next slide please and what's so
interesting about that is this
when you know that you have your bases
covered meaning you have a firm
foundation
that you've already set aside money to
hedge that will allow you to go full
throttle in your investments
you can even invest in investments that
people think are so risky but because
you've protected your basis say that
even if
you can take riskier bets because you
have a good foundation
next slide please um investing is about
long-term capital appreciation next
slide
and here's the thing i i just want to
say this that
stocks bonds forex property business
insurance you all need them
it's not a question which is the best
investment it's a question of
which investment will complement your
portfolio
because what the strength of one will
will also complement the weakness of the
other
so people obviously i don't know
investments
don't do that it's all about finding
what investment will work the best for
you
next slide please so so with that
uh what is vul or variable used life to
me next slide
number one is a head hedge of protection
in the prime years of my life
next slide it allows me to go all
in on my investments and businesses
because i know i've covered my base as
well
next slide it gives me or my family cash
cash flow should things not go the way i
wanted please do note that
what's so what's so unique about a vul
is it gives you offense that it gives
you an investment component but it also
gives you defense
that when things don't go your way
you're protected next slide
it can replace my active income sources
if i could not know
if i could not work anymore next slide
and the investment component gives me a
level of cash that i can use for my
future goal and for most of you it's
retirement
next slide so should you have life
insurance should you get vul
next slide please so in my opinion
it's not a question whether you should
get one but it's a question of finding
what
fits you and what your goals are because
we all have goals and we need to find
something that's
a sweet spot to meet our needs and to
meet our goals as well
next slide please so you put money in
life insurance to protect you but you
also have an investment component that
can maximize what you already have
next slide so to close i just want to
show this picture
uh this is a tree in jerusalem that
while we were walking the tour guide
pointed that
this olive tree has been there for over
2000 years already
so while a lot of people were shocked
whoa this is 2000 years
a financial nugget of information came
into my mind
which was this i could never count and i
could never
guess if there were millions or hundreds
of thousands of olive fruits that came
out from the tree i will never i will
never know i will never know how
how how much has come out from that but
there's one thing that i do know
all of the fruits that came out from
that started with one seed one seed that
was planted in the ground one seed that
instead of being consumed or wasted
it was something that was put in and
what i want to submit to you is this
your future is in what's in your hand
right now don't wait for things to get
better put it in the ground
invest it and wait because the biggest
trees
take time this is not get rich quick but
this is get rich
right this is not you putting it in the
ground and
hoping that because
once you put it in and once it starts to
get bigger
you will never know how many generations
of filipinos
in your family will be better because
right smack in the middle of 2021 you
started thinking about your future you
started to invest you started
to plant when there was uncertainty when
everyone did not want to do it
and it's high time know that all 1000 of
us
in the prime years of our lives put in
and double down because there will come
a point in time when we're older
we don't get to do this anymore and if
there's one thing i know about investing
it's all about time
don't waste the time that you have keep
on putting it
on the ground and let your money work
hard for you so
thank you so much um mandela for
inviting me i hope you guys learned a
lot from this and god bless you all
wow thank you very much marvin all those
important tips
i'm just give me a second
and sorry about that seem to get my own
feedback here
okay
let's lower this a little bit all right
marvin sorry about that
i got a little bit uh feedback here in
my end but that was just such a
fascinating fascinating the
um discussion am i okay martin do i have
audio there
okay sorry about that and you know
speaking of investments
you went through a whole plethora of
investments for us and um
i just wanted to point out that while
i'm not a financial advisor myself
i can tell you this that the investment
you make right now we'll pay off in the
end of this because we're giving away 5
000 pesos worth of sodexo
gcs also we'll be giving away some uh
tickets to the
virtual concert of sarah geronimo's also
manulife policy owner since 2015.
more of that is coming up of course
later on but
uh in the meantime i just think that
we've just got so much that we have to
get through here
and getting a life insurance with
investment plan
should not be perceived as a burden but
rather as
a necessities great points made by our
speakers uh both for your financial
growth and preparation for your
retirement
and also safeguarding your family from
risks
therefore ensuring peace of mind
now i know there's so much to absorb but
just try to because this is solid gold
what we're doing here and before we move
on to our next segment
i would just like you all to pause for a
moment and just watch this video
about one of manulife's best-selling dul
products
you deserve the best life you work hard
you know the formula for success
your options are wide but few make the
cut
we can help you make the most out of
life
[Music]
because you deserve the privilege that
comes with building an elite life
introducing manulife affluence max elite
this one-time investment in life
insurance plan provides you with a
startup bonus
that would optimize your funds on the
onset so you can enjoy rewards now
and in the future experience the
manulife
affluence max elite advantage
[Music]
let's say you put in a one-time
investment of one million pesos
manulife will give you one percent of
that as a startup bonus
this increases your investment by ten
thousand pesos
assuming that the funds grow by eight
percent your investment can grow to
almost
five million pesos
get a loyalty bonus if you stay invested
you may have the chance to get a loyalty
bonus on the 10th
15th and the 20th year
enjoy hassle-free application through a
guaranteed issue offer
this means that there would be no need
for medical examinations
if certain conditions are met
get a boost on your investment by making
additional investments
anytime enjoy peace of mind with life
insurance coverage
invest through manulife affluence max
elite
get an early reward and look forward to
more
and if you want to know more about this
product and you have an existing
financial advisor please schedule a call
or expect a message from them
right after this webinar and for those
who already have a vol
plan with mana life well you can check
your fund performance
through manulife online
manulife online lets you view and manage
your insurance policies
wherever you are and whenever you need
to
pardon me you lost this second whenever
you need to
for those of you who are already uh with
the manulife policy
try doing this through your manual life
online policy because it is a very very
good way
to get uh checking into your account
manulife
online lets you view and it lets you
manage your insurance policies wherever
you are
and whenever you need to which is very
very important in
of course managing all your money but
we've also got some very exciting things
we've also got a qr code here
just scan that qr cor code register
online to manulife
online and here's the part i was talking
about a little earlier
about the investment we've got 1 000
pesos
gift certificates that are going to be
given out as well
and you may access your manulife on
count account by doing
that and we will be doing five winners
we're picking five winners of one
thousand pesos
egcs from today's webinars attendees now
speaking of policy owners
we're also giving away two tickets for
the virtual concert
of brand ambassador and manulife policy
holder since 2015
sarah geronimo this will be on march 27
and winners of concert tickets will
receive an email
from a manulife representative straight
after
this webinar and now for those without a
financial advisor yet
well you may reach out to us by the
contact details that are flashed on your
screen right now
trust me we'll make it worth your while
if you do that so keep those numbers
handy or all those digits and the email
address
and send us a bit of a message on
manulife.com dot
ph right or you can visit all of the
manulife branches
nationwide of course first your health
and safety is our priority
so just make sure it's safe to do so
before you do that otherwise
you can go down to virtual avenue and
that's a whole lot safer
now let me call back our speakers zed
matubish and marvin gurmo
for our panel discussion gentlemen
welcome
back hi
hi again my brain's exploding i don't
know about you if this is just another
day in the office for you
i'm just i don't even know where to
store all the information you've given
us but
we're seeing a lot of questions from our
viewers but
before we go to that uh let's have a
quick panel interview
just to make sense of it and maybe put
some in layman's terms i know our
audience are very engaged
and also very informed but let's see if
we can break it down my first question
is for zed earlier in our poll we asked
our viewers
what they're currently investing and a
lot of people
answered some some pretty great things
and insurance is one of them
i want to know what you think about this
first of all james i'm
quite happy that bank td wasn't the
number one answer
a few years ago that would have been the
case
but seeing the the results and
particularly because insurance is the
number one answer
i'm very happy because this goes to show
you that how much we have improved as an
investing public in terms of knowledge
and ability or the decision to
buy more insurance which is very
important for
uh securing uh your future thanks ed now
marvin um how about how popular is vul
compared to other investment vehicles i
mean there's
an impression that variable universal
life plan
is not that popular compared to other
financial tools despite
its advantages what can you say about
that or
what advice can you give to those who
are still hesitant
to invest in bul because of the
commitment needed to pay premiums within
a certain
number of years
you're on mute that's the 2020
2021 saying of the year you're on mute
it's okay well i think am i back oh hey
there
it's it's popular to me in a way that it
was one of the first investments that
i even invested into i went into that
way before
uh stock market way before
cryptocurrency so
uh it's a very very good in my opinion
it's a very very good way also to get
your feet wet especially if you have a
financial advisor who's hand holding you
in the process that when markets are
down financial advisor could also give
you someone advice on what's happening
and i think that's the added
uh bonus of it also that it's not just
you
going through the financial journey by
yourself you have people who could give
you also sound strategies
on what you're supposed to do so um to
piggyback on that also
um i i believe that it it forms a part
of your portfolio
that it will complement other portions
it's what i is what i've mentioned there
are investments for growth there are
investments for hedging
there are investments for cash flow and
a vul
can give you growth and hedging at the
same time
so some something like that
thank you very much and now our next
question is for zed
do you think filipinos in general lack
confidence in investing
are most risk averse or is it just more
lack of knowledge in education about
various investment options
james i believe filipinos in general are
starting to get more confidence
and get more starting to get more
knowledge about investing
we we are still not where we want to be
ideally
a lot of data will probably show us that
the philippines is
behind our neighbors when it comes to
having insurance or investments for
retirement but i think more and more
filipinos are
thinking about these things more so it
is very important you know for
institutions
like manulife and their advisors to be
ready to support this growing demand for
knowledge and that also includes marvin
here who's
been very helpful with with his books
and his webinars
very very very helpful indeed yeah
okay so uh perhaps this next one
uh well either but since vul products
rely on market movement
is it safe to get one in times of a
pandemic like
right now marvin
it always goes back to what your
timeline is number one if
if you have the money and you don't need
it and your cash flow is not
interrupted and your timeline is very
very long i would say that in times of
uncertainty this allows you to
accumulate right now when prices
are low the problem is when there's no
pandemic people
would always say that the market is too
high everything's so expensive i can't
buy anything
well here's the thing right now we don't
know when
things will recover but this is what i
do know
we are much much lower than where we
were before so if you want to position
and wait for the recovery then i really
believe that this is a
time for you to get prices lower
especially if your timeline is very very
long
as well great great great
awesome stuff um all right so many
questions here i'm i'm
i'm looking at all these screens because
so many people are engaged and the
questions are just
through the roof uh here's another one
when do you experience roi with vul i
mean if my money is in there for for 20
years
will i be sure that my money would have
earned is it fair to say that
marvin perhaps you can continue um okay
uh here's how you segment it similar to
what i mentioned
uh during the talk that uh your your
goal
should not be to look at the roi first
your goal is to match it with
whatever need you would have because
this is what i believe uh gains and
returns are just a by-product of what
your strategy is so
let me put context to that if your
investment horizon is 20 years
uh that's what you as what you've
mentioned there you look at what amount
of
money am i targeting for this 20-year
horizon is it 10 million is it 15
million is it 20
is it 20 million and the technique there
is this the closer you are
to that or that amount that you're
trying to get
already you start to shift it already to
investments that are less volatile
because
as what we talked about earlier uh
volatility
happens it's normal it's part of the
game and you want volatility
at the early parts of your investing
cycle so that you get to buy things
cheaper
but as you get older the technique there
is just to shift it into
other products that are less volatile so
that should a crash happen
later on uh you won't be as hit and you
would still
come out earning money especially if
i'll say i forgot to mention this
during crashes you just keep on
accumulating
and keep on buying when the market is
cheaper and when the market is expensive
uh that's when you can start saving a
bit more as when it gets cheaper you add
again
so that when the 20-year time horizon is
up you will be in a much much better
position
okay just a quick follow-up marvin about
the vul um
they offered companies uh offered
top-ups right
what does that mean and is it something
that you advise
okay that's that's very interesting
because that's that was my strategy when
i was starting out so normally when you
get a plan
there's a fixed amount that you need to
put in either on a quarterly basis
or on a yearly basis a top-up is
basically you putting something
above and beyond that so for example you
you've uh
you've dedicated to put a hundred
thousand per year a top-up is something
that you would put in excess
of that and i challenge everyone when
you have your bonuses
when you have your 13-month pay you
treat that as a bonus and that's what
you put in as your top up
because every time you top up it allows
you to buy more shares and that's what
what we've been talking about it's all
about accumulating
and it's all about building a larger
base so uh
i've been doing it i've been living it
it works
if you have extra your bonus top it up
good advice right there thank you very
much zed and marvin for your very
comprehensive
and also very insightful answers now
guys it's still not too late to hit the
q
a box despite all the questions we're
getting we want to encourage you to ask
yours
and get your questions answered by our
speakers right now
we're getting a lot of great questions
from the audience and i'm also excited
to hear our guests answer all these but
before that
make sure to stay tuned until the end of
the webinar because manulife philippines
is giving away
that those gift certificates i keep
mentioning worth 5 000 pesos so
watch out for that now before we proceed
to the q a
we would like to of course first
acknowledge the presence of our friends
who have attended uh here from the media
so a big
shout out to all of our guests out there
uh from the manila standard
we have from business world sparkup we
have theac
and uh for all of those who are tuned in
thank you so much we're really really
grateful that you're joining us
it makes this whole webinar just
worthwhile now we're ready to bring back
zed and marvin on screen for our q a
segments
gentlemen you're in the hot seat i hope
you're all ready because this is just
going to fly we're just going to fly
live with this we're going to take
questions from the audience
i have a ton of questions here for our
from
everywhere right so the first question
um
is coming from i can't read the name but
the question is
from marvin here we go why is it crucial
to diversify investments right
there's a follow-up for an average
person where investing seems complicated
how to start um
number one diversification also is
dependent on
how big your cash position is or how big
your portfolio is but
um similar to what we talked about uh in
in the webinar that
a vul and equity fund already gives you
bits and pieces of diversification
already so
uh one one way for you to determine if
you're ready to diversify into another
asset class is
for example uh your your exposure to
this particular asset is too big already
and you're not so comfortable
to have that lar that amount of money
just for example in real estate
so you you might think that i may
need to diversify already further so
that i'm not purely exposed to this
particular
asset class so you can look at your
comfort level
you could look at your exposure that i'm
i
am i being too aggressive in this
particular investment that if this
investment collapses and
if everything is there it will
my portfolio
so that's how you can look at it it's a
case-to-case basis people would put
numbers to it but my suggestion is just
just to try to uh play it on your
comfort level
uh but generally speaking a vul is
something that's already diversified
especially if you
have something spread across bonds and
you have something spread across
the 30 plus companies that are in our
index at the 30 companies in our index
thank you marvin uh zed we have a
question for you
once again from our media friends and
this question says based on the market
update
what would you recommend where to invest
our funds it's a pretty broad question
but uh
take a good stab at it well yeah as as
marvin also mentioned
and also as i mentioned also we we are
fairly positive in the equities market
uh
right now again it will all depend on
your conversation with your
uh with your financial advisor um it
will depend on your ability to take
risks your ability
to uh your your investment horizon your
financial goals
uh but again generally speaking we we
like what we we see that can happen in
the long term
in the philippine stock market okay
great
and let's fly through some more of these
because they're just pouring in i tell
you
uh we've asked already about why it's
crucial to diversify
let's go straight into you sir marvin
you mentioned that you first
invested in life insurance vol may we
know how it's going after 14 years
i know you've kind of answered it but uh
perhaps a refresher
yep it's it's it's good because what you
invested
early on build allows you to build a
base already so
in times that the markets were lower uh
those investments that i placed in were
the ones that
are pulling my gains also for today so
uh yeah it's i'm
i'm quite satisfied with it great
i love the uh analogy used or the little
nugget financial nugget you got from the
tree because i think that that spells
out a lot i'm sure that tree like you
said
you mentioned about the the fruit and
how much fruit and that started from one
seed
but i'm sure there were times when that
tree was down and not producing fruit
i'm sure there were times
when that tree didn't look as healthy as
it was today but if you're spreading it
out i think that's the message i'm
getting from both of you
it's it's understanding your goals what
you want to do with it
and then you ride out those times
because if you're so obsessed with the
little dips and drops and peaks and
valleys it's
i like the way you put it too you become
an employee again and that's the whole
point of
investing is to liberate ourselves from
that
okay uh more questions here um
piling through bear with me because like
i said i've got like
three or four screens open because
that's what it takes now
to address this very engaged crowd that
we've got here
okay so um running through a few more
where do we have these ones here
these are just i'm so excited because
now it's also a time that i've just
started getting into investments myself
so i'm on a selfish part absorbing a lot
of the information for myself
and so a lot of these questions here let
me just get this one over here
okay
and if you could see my screens you'd
understand why i'm going through all of
this
there's literally thousands we got 1 500
people tuned in
and everyone's trying to ask a question
at the same time and i'm dying to get
all of them so just
recently started earning and would like
to invest some of my savings it's not a
lot
but i will be able to invest in vul for
just about
3 000 a month is that enough is that
okay
marvin i mentioned earlier that
investing is about building a base but
so i assume that you
you just started working meaning you're
in your early 20s
you have something that a lot of people
don't have you may have a smaller salary
but you have time
meaning putting 3 000 and increasing it
every time you earn more you get a
promotion you transfer you get a bonus
will go a very very long way so if
you're you'll ask me
you between you a 20 year old who's just
starting putting in 3 000 pesos then a
55 year old putting a larger amount of
money
that thinking point when you reach 55
and 60 years old also you would have put
in more money because of the amount of
time that you have
so don't despise small beginnings start
what with what you have
because investing is also about the
disciplining it's never about how big it
is at the start but it's about
you know you know james what the biggest
problem of filipinos are when they
invest
is when they invest
but the discipline there is to put in
money
put it back in let it compound and then
if you have extra
you just keep on piling it until it
becomes something that becomes so big
that it's so beneficial for you already
it's not there okay all right i hope i
had that problem one day
i pray for problems when you i was gonna
say when you invested that's why the
rich get richer because james is
investing and
all right um i i'm blushing now
okay uh zed question for you again
pretty pretty bold and pretty
general but fearless prediction when do
you think the market will fully recover
yeah um our view as mentioned earlier is
that markets are poised for recovery in
on the back of expectations of the
reopening of the economy and
optimism with the vaccine as to the
question
when the psei will actually reach
the levels that we saw january 2020 for
example
that was that is still uncertain this
will really depend
on a lot of factors catalysts and risks
that we mentioned earlier
all right that's good that's that's good
great way to answer it if i
another question here this one's for
marvin i believe if i already have a
traditional life insurance
product for my protection needs and i
want to invest would it still be worth
putting in my money in an investment
linked
insurance plan that's a that's that's a
very very good question but that's also
something that's very
personal i can share things that i did i
have both
because uh there are certain merits for
a traditional life insurance and there
are certain merits also for
a variable you you needed linked
insurance so if you are the type of
person
that you still you want that growth and
whatever is in your fund gets protected
because it's part of
an insurance and then you also want that
investment to be
up protected will help your estate to
give you a certain level of protection
later on
then then a vul will work very very well
for you so
my suggestion is whoever invited you
here uh
talk to them uh so that they can drill
down what are your specific needs
because
uh it will always go back to another
young kailangan
a network solution for that so if you're
asking me i have
both because they complement my
portfolio
so better drill down also and look at
how much
you need right now and what are the
types of uh
of of the ul's that will also work hard
for you right now
okay great stuff zed a question for you
um does no guarantee in returns
mean that there is a chance that my
investment might be depleted
or reach zero value
james that's a good question uh in the
realm of the theoretical
obviously that can happen but uh within
the limits of reality
uh the chances of that happening is very
close to zero
because of three things uh one uh
companies and securities that we have or
our fund managers have historically
invested in have
low to zero bankruptcy or default rates
number two um when you invest in a
pulled fund like a vol
you like what uh marvin mentioned
earlier you immediately get diversified
20 to 30 securities at a time when you
just invest in one
one product so technically you need all
of these 20 to 30 companies to
you know to go bankrupt at the same time
which is again very very unlikely
and then third and i think this is the
most important reason is that
the fund manager uses fundamental uh
investment
okay i'm having an echo so sorry about
that
so uh and then the third reason is
active fund management and then the
third reason is
will actually uh means that the fund
manager will have
uh the ability to identify
the differences
okay we did get a little bit of feedback
there but we didn't understand
a little bit of feedback there but we
did understand now i'm getting it
now i'm getting it right well you know
what the information's so valuable we
have to say well i know what the
information is so valuable we have to
say it twice
now this question here is it true now
this question here is it true
that life insurance proceeds is tax-free
how can i take advantage of this how can
i take advantage of this
i'm playing with i'm i'm working with
the echo here playing i'm working with
the echo here
marvin marvin okay oh yeah so sorry it's
a bit delayed
um yeah what's what's nice what's nice
about that is
uh the insurance component um and you
add that to your fund if something
happens
to you especially if it's irrevocable uh
that
those are mainly tax free already and
that's
that's that's an advantage especially if
you are in the latter years of your life
already when you need
when something happens your family would
need to pay a state taxes
uh that insurance component that stacks
free uh
is something that they can get readily
and they can use already for whatever
expenses or proceeds that they would
need to use uh later on so
that's why i mentioned at the start that
it there are certain advantages for some
investments that give you a hedge
they may not be something that's super
sexy that will give you growth
but in times that you need certain
levels of protection like uh protection
from taxes
as well uh this is a very very good way
for you to get
tax benefits or at least have an
investment that stacks free
all right uh let's see right more
questions
still getting it still getting it
i'll try and i'll try doing something on
my end i'll try doing something on my
head
the second is
okay
it seems to still be there but it seems
to be there but
anyway
we're trying to fix it it's just
inspiring to be there such
engaged viewers so i'd like to take this
opportunity to thank
once again to those who have sent in
their questions i'm sure you've got some
great insights from our experts just
like i did over here
and i'm sure everybody tuned in because
we've been getting a lot of messages as
well
zed marvin i'll leave you both to give
your final words for our viewers
before we end our q and a sessions
thanks thanks james um thanks thanks
james
marvin i'll go i'll i'll speak first
i'll
speak first my final message to the
audience
my final message to the audience is to
invest long term
is to invest long term diversify
take advantage of the opportunities
available in 2021
and finally please consider manulife as
your partner in achieving your financial
goals
thank you thank you very much zed
we're going to try one more thing here
maybe this is
before i bring marvin up
okay am i back okay uh what a lot of
people regarded 20 20 yes a year that
was so bad
and what i want to submit to all of you
is use 2021 as a year for you to bounce
back
because i really believe that there's so
much opportunity
right here right now in the midst of the
uncertainty
and let's not wait for things to get
better is what i've mentioned at the
start
but do what you can do your best with
the resources that you have
save and invest because everything that
you need to prosper is already right
within you
it's either you work hard for it and as
you start to work hard don't spend it
just save it and invest it because
at the end of the day time is one of
your greatest assets
and use what you can right now to put it
in the ground
to make your money work hard for you and
i really do hope that
2021 as you look back at this date this
was the year this was your turning point
that you were able to push forward to
whatever dreams that you have
in getting financial freedom so thank
you so much also manulife for having me
james thank you
well thank you too very much zev
just before we announce the winner of
the raffle prize
[Music]
show the result of the last poll
hi vanessa can you hear me can you hear
me
hi james hi james yes and the echo
is so cute earlier we asked our audience
this question
what is your investment appetite this
and uh the choices are a confident
b not too confident i need advice from
an expert
so good to know the majority of you here
are confident
and actually it's 52
i hope most of us here will be better
smarter investors
after hearing our speakers remember vul
can help us not only to protect our
hard-earned money
but also to protect our families from
life's uncertainties
as well now for those who are not
confident
don't worry it's not too late to consult
a financial expert to help you assess
market condition
your needs and the right product that
address your needs
and your budget now we are here to be
more
confident when it comes to investing now
i'm sure
a lot of us here became better smarter
investors
after hearing our speakers earlier talk
about the market outlook
for 2021 and how be well can actually
help us not only to protect our families
but also life's uncertainties but
also our hard earned money now thank you
everyone for participating in our fall
back to you james okay thank you very
much vanessa
and now it's time to show our winner for
this afternoon's
final raffle draw how exciting is this
i've been
press releasing this for a long time so
i'm super excited about 5 000
pesos worth of sodexo and that goes to
johann musico that's musical to your
ears i'm sure this is going to be
great this is as good as cash i tell you
you're going to be spending on stuff
you're really going to need so
a representative from the manulife team
will reach out to you on how to claim
your prize johan
so just hang tight sit tight for that
and would now like to thank everyone who
joined us this afternoon
for taking the time and also more
importantly for
actively participating during our q and
a segment
it was just incredible i mean i wish we
could have gotten through all your
questions it was so engaging
and i was just very impressed by all of
the the level of questions that were
coming in
we hope that this webinar inspired you
to make better decisions in
investing in insurance so you can live
easier today
and live every day better even through
retirement
and that wraps up this afternoon's
financial wellness webinar
this has been your host ladies and
gentlemen my name is james deakin
watch out for future webinars of
manulife philippines
together through their facebook page
keep an eye out for that
there it is on your screen i will just
leave you now
with a very quick post-event survey to
help us know
how you found today's webinar all you
have to do is simply scan the qr code
flash on your screen right now and it'll
lead you to the rest together with
manulife we can live
every day better and with the right life
insurance
and investment plan thank you very much
once again maraming salamat
stay safe everyone see you next time
[Music]
uh
do
come on
you deserve the best life you work hard
you know the formula for success
your options are wide but few make the
cut
we can help you make the most out of
life
because you deserve the privilege that
comes with building
an elite life introducing manulife
affluence max
elite this one-time investment in life
insurance plan
provides you with a startup bonus that
would optimize your funds on the onset
so you can enjoy rewards now and in the
future
experience the manulife affluence max
elite advantage
let's say you put in a one-time
investment of one million pesos
manulife will give you one percent of
that as a startup bonus
this increases your investment by ten
thousand pesos
assuming that the funds grow by eight
percent your investment can grow to
almost five million pesos
[Music]
get a loyalty bonus if you stay invested
you may have the chance to get a loyalty
bonus on the 10th
15th and on the 20th year
enjoy hassle-free application through a
guaranteed issue
offer this means that there would be no
need for medical examinations if certain
conditions
are met get a boost on your investment
by making additional investments anytime
enjoy peace of mind with life insurance
coverage
invest through manulife affluence max
elite
get an early reward and look forward to
more
[Music]
catch up with me
happy birthday
fun
[Music]
but she was there to keep my spirits up
for that thank fuller
[Music]
hi la i know ready enough for 2021
you